<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Pratik Bhandari</title>
<link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Pratik&#39;s view of the horizon from the mountaintop</description>
<image>
<url>https://pratikb.com/me.jpg</url>
<title>Pratik Bhandari</title>
<link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/index.html</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 18:15:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Identity enigma</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-12-16_movie-primer/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<p>Sci-fi movies have always captivated me, especially those that delve into time travel. Gone are the days when the mere presence of a time travel gadget or a loop day would impress most people.</p>
<p>With a meagre investment of only $7000, Shane Carruth directed and produced the remarkable movie “Primer” (2005), which earned the Grand Jury Prize at the 2004 Sundance Film Festival.</p>
<p>Unlike a typical time travel flick where the protagonist uses a machine to traverse backwards or forward in time or possesses the superpower to navigate past, present, and future, “Primer” offers a unique plot. Protagonists Aron and Abe discover time travel through the machine they invent, a time box, which essentially creates at least two versions of the same person. Aron and Abe exploit the box by making profitable stock trades, apparently with the success of putting their old selves in the box, quite literally.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-12-16_movie-primer/primer-timeline.svg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Method of timetravel in Primer</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><em>By derivative work: Tom-b (talk)Time_Travel_Method.jpg: Original uploader was William lee0 at en.wikipedia - <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=5311985">Time_Travel_Method</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/deed.en">CC BY-SA 3.0</a></em></p>
<!-- At this point, I already have a question: which is thre real Aron and Abe and why? 
 Does this question sound familiar? Hold on to it. -->
<p>Hold your thoughts.</p>
<p>Multiple versions of Aron and Abe co-exist in the later days. As a viewer, it becomes harder to discern which pair is the original. And this hits the nail on the head of the entire time-travel enterprise of the movie for us.</p>
<p>Say that in an instance of time travel in the movie, a duplicate of Aron is formed. What is there to say that this iteration’s Aron is <em>less real</em> than the “original” Aron? The duplicate retains all previous memories, experiences, and consciousness; all iterations are essentially identical!</p>
<p align="center">
<img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-12-16_movie-primer/https:/raw.githubusercontent.com/pratik-bhandari/art/main/img/handpicked/2022-02-20-20-01_seed_4018.png" alt="Generative art" width="75%">
</p>
<p>
<em>© Pratik Bhandari,</em> <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">CC BY-NC-ND 4.0</a>
</p>
<!-- ![Generarive art](https://raw.githubusercontent.com/pratik-bhandari/art/main/img/handpicked/2022-02-20-20-01_seed_4018.png){fig-align="center"} 
*©Pratik Bhandari, CC BY-NC-ND 4.0*  -->
<p>The movie’s subtle response to this, among many questions, is suggested in the airport scene. Aron leaves the town, while Abe wishes to remain. A heated argument ensues regarding what to do about the “problem” of the other originals/duplicates: to leave them be or address the situation. Perhaps Shane Carruth intended to convey that all duplicates possess their unique identity until their formation, after which new stimuli influence their individuality. They are free to take different, independent roads.</p>
<p>Is this question pointed out above any different than the Teletransportation paradox? Without being a philosopher, it seems like “Primer” also grapples with the Teletransportataion paradox, albeit with a fresh perspective on the issues of identity and consciousness. Instead of asking if you remain the same person when disassembled here and reformed on Mars atom by atom, <strong>“Primer” asks a different question</strong>. If an identical copy of “you” is created, which one is the <em>real</em> you? To phrase it differently, if you wake up and find a duplicate version of yourself, which of you would be you? All to say, “Primer” also showcases a different face of the Teletransportation paradox.</p>
<p>Movies may not be the getaway place to find solutions to the philosophical quandaries of the mind, consciousness, and identity. But sometimes, it is “fun” looking out from someone else’s artistic lens. Expands your horizon. The problem of consciousness may not be solved in the next twenty-five years. But “identity”? It is more than an academic estimation to bet on a bottle of wine. <em>Identity</em> extends beyond personal, national, and second person observation in behavioural sciences. We will try to talk about these them next time, hopefully with some experts. Aren’t we all experts in a way, after all?</p>
<p>Thoughts? <a href="../../../contact.html">Get in touch.</a></p>
<!-- <strong>
<i class="bi bi-envelope-at"></i>
<a href="mailto:writer@pratikb.com">
<code>writer@pratikb.com</code></a></strong> -->
<hr>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>tv</category>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>science</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <category>2023</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-12-16_movie-primer/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflections on farewells and returns</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-08-14_live-n-leave/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-08-14_live-n-leave/fly-hills.png" alt="A person standing on a snowy mountain seems to be looking at a hot air balloon in the sky." style="width:86%" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">
To leave or not to leave (Photo credit: Plagiarised by DALL·E 2)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>A poignant scene from Interstellar shows an unfolding of heartache between Murph and Cooper:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Murph: You have no idea when you’re coming back. No idea at all!</p>
<p>Murph throws the watch and turns her back.</p>
<p>Cooper: Don’t make leave like this, Murph. Please. I have to go now.</p>
<p>Murph will not turn around. Cooper tries to rest his hand on the back of her head, but she shakes it off.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This exchange between a departing father and his reluctant daughter strikes a chord reminding me of my own predicament.</p>
<p>For almost fifteen years, I have been living far from home. There is no set timetable for a return visit to spend time with my family. No schedule is ever fixed. And whenever I am home, I depart without knowing when I’ll be back again. Just like Cooper, my returns are uncertain. And just like Murph, my family knows it very well. I can’t look in their tearful eyes when I leave. Else, I’d have said, “Don’t make me leave like this”.</p>
<p>Maybe that’s why this scene got me in tears.</p>
<p>When you are away from home, time runs differently. You become a ghost. New people don’t know you, old ones have a faint memory of your existence. You live in a new dimension. Friends become strangers, and strangers become friends.</p>
<p>What happens when I return? Sometimes I feel like I never left. Everything appears fresh and unchanged. Yet, many a time, I feel I’ve returned after spending an eternity in a strange world. I witness what I did not witness, things I missed: funerals unattended, weddings uncelebrated. New kids in the neighbourhood. New houses erected with new families, new faces. I ask where the old ones are. People die, migrate, and move on – much like me. To some, I’m the newcomer; they are newcomers to me. I claim, without voicing, that the place belongs to me, my childhood and my memory. Being new means a never-ending cycle of introductions and re-introductions. Names and faces unpair when you don’t see or talk with someone for many years. This unpairing always gives a sense of being a stranger. I have not yet gotten used to being <em>new</em>, being a stranger in my own place. Attachment is cruel.</p>
<p>Reality comes and bites you. Continents away, you witness your parents’ ageing and ailing health from a distance. As a parent, maybe they wished to see their child grow up. As a child, I don’t want my parents to grow old and fragile – youthful yearning. Nature takes its course: Every time I go home, I see my parents getting older and older. I can’t do anything about it while they are declining. It is painful – not being there with the people I love while perceiving a rapid advance of their time. Technology will only take you so far.</p>
<p>There is a trade-off in living away from home. In a developed country, working a white-colour job, some aspects of life are ostensibly better than back at home. Your priorities determine what pain you are willing to tolerate. Time and again, one has to revisit and reevaluate the priorities… and take off… a fresh start.</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>2023</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-08-14_live-n-leave/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2023 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-08-14_live-n-leave/fly-hills.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhD defence: An afterthought</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-01-21_phd-afterthought/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-01-21_phd-afterthought/buddha-hat.png" alt="Silhouette of Buddha wearing a convocation hat." style="width:85%" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">
“What is PhD, if not knowledge expanding.” Enlightening or not, it can be enjoyable. (Image generated from DALL·E 2)
</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>I defended my PhD <a href="https://pratik-bhandari.github.io/contents/html-phd/">thesis</a> last month on the 7th of December, 2022. The program was organised at 8 am to adjust for the time difference between Germany and New Zealand. I was defending from Germany, and two out of five of my committee members were attending online from New Zealand. There were 20-plus online attendees. And 50-plus people, including two committee members, attended the defence in person. I was surprised so many people came, online and in person, so early in the morning. It was quite a big event for me.</p>
<section id="pre-defence" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pre-defence">Pre-defence</h2>
<section id="worries" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="worries">Worries</h3>
<p>Worry and nervousness were fluctuating. Three weeks before the defence, I was slightly anxious. It subsided the following week. The week before the defence, I started to become nervous. Many questions occupied my mind. What if I can’t answer committee members’ questions in front of so many people? (What if no one attends?) What if they ask questions referring to a specific page number and sentence? Can I defend each sentence while everyone watches me? What if I fumble too much, which I tend to do when nervous? What if I can’t answer the questions? What if my answers do not satisfy them? Will I and my presentation be clear and understandable to those committee members who are not remotely close to language sciences, let alone my specific line of work? Should I ask my parents and friends not to come to the defence because it would be humiliating and embarrassing for everyone?</p>
<p>Okay. I let you into my secret and darkest thoughts. Read further. Now, what next?</p>
<p>I was having trouble finding a room with a hybrid — online and in-person — facility. Any room with such functionality was already booked for the day. Somehow, I got a room in the middle of the forest, away from the centre of the university. It was worrisome that the online system did not work on the first try. It took two days to make it work: There was no IT support. It is ridiculous that the student has to organize everything for their defence, and the University does not do it as far as I know.</p>
<p>There is a tradition of serving food and drink on the day of defence after the defence is over. I had to plan what to bring and where from. It is quite simple, but amid the nervousness about the defence (presentation and Q&amp;A), it became a big deal. Not everything was as bad as it sounds here, or that it can’t be overcome<sup>1</sup>.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-defence" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-defence">The defence</h2>
<p>Let’s talk about the defence: my presentation and the Q&amp;A session. I was allocated 30 minutes to talk about four years of research. It was followed by an hour-long Q&amp;A session. In that hour, the committee members asked plenty of questions, some expected and some unexpected. (One committee member, who was in Saarbrücken, didn’t attend in person. I assumed he would; I never asked.) At that time, I couldn’t have guessed how long the Q&amp;A had lasted: It neither felt like an eternity nor did it feel like a blink of an eye.</p>
<section id="presentation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="presentation">Presentation</h3>
<p>I had my notes for the PowerPoint presentation in the speaker notes. Trying to peek at it was distracting at times: Such was not the case in the earlier practice talks I had given in front of my colleagues and friends. The microphones on the podium were very distracting in the presentation. I felt like I had to hear my voice from the overhead loudspeakers; otherwise, the audience wouldn’t hear me. But I realised later that it wasn’t the case. The online audience could hear me via the “room mic” placed near me. The in-person audience could have heard me even without the loudspeakers.</p>
<p>I also lost my train of thought at least three points throughout the presentation, which means I likely said something random to get back on track. (Later people in the audience reported that they didn’t notice anything like that. Well, I guess they were being polite to me. After all, I had already passed when I asked if they’d noticed me lose focus.) I’m saying now that I couldn’t deliver everything as I’d planned then.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-qa-round" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-qa-round">The Q&amp;A round</h3>
<p>The word <em>“defence”</em> makes it sound as if someone is attacking you, and you are protecting yourself from the attack. We are programmed to feel that way from the time when we learn about dissertation, thesis, passing PhD, and …defence. Okay, so how did it go in my case? Not as bad as I had imagined the worse case scenario to be. It went well. Some questions were anticipated, some not, and some: I had no clue how to answer. I believe all questions of different flavours are asked to test how a “defendant” responds in an intellectual/academic discussion. You should be ready to answer, or at least respond, to everything, sensibly. Is that what we get evaluated on? I digress.</p>
<p>In general, I felt I could have answered many questions better than how and what I did. Good thing: I waited to reply after the question was asked. Didn’t rush. Most of the time, I took some time to think through the questions, and sketched in a notepad what the answers could be. Then I responded. This approach was very beneficial when the questions were tricky and unanticipated and when I had never before looked at my studies from a particular point of view raised by the committee members. I heard that some audience members didn’t like me “writing something” before answering the question, as if I was “writing a book”. I don’t know what the committee members thought. And I don’t remember clearly if I even mentioned to the committee what I was doing. Maybe I didn’t. A mistake?</p>
<p>The difficult and a bit problematic part was coordinating between online and in-person committee members when they were asking questions. In principle, it is the committee Chair’s job to manage and organise who asks questions and for how long. But the mic in the room didn’t pick up the Chair’s voice, so I had to reiterate what he said to the online committee members. It could have been smoother than it was, had everyone been present in person. I could not pay attentiontion to the online audience, my friends and families, after the presentation when I (and everyone in the room) was asked to leave the room for the committee members to decide the fate of my PhD.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="what-am-i-preaching-here" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-am-i-preaching-here">What am I preaching here?</h2>
<p>(C’mon, don’t take it literally. I am not preaching!)</p>
<p>The committee called me in after some minutes. There were some secret vows I had to make to obtain doctoral degree :P (Nothing like that.) They told I passed with good grades :) Felt happy for some minutes; don’t ask what the feeling was after those fleeting moments. With the benefit of hindsight, all the worries and nervousness and anxiety seem to be too intense than they could have been should have been. It is natural and maybe necessary to be worried to some extent, but not too much. Having said that, if I travelled back in time before the defence and told myself not to worry so much, I doubt I would be any less worried or anxious.</p>
<p>I saved myself some trouble by taking advice from those who had gone through a similar phase before me. There are also plenty of instances where I could still have done better. Based on others’ and my experiences, I would recommend the following, in no particular order, to someone who plans to defend their thesis:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Do as many dry runs as possible. Present it to your lab members; get the bad news at home. Also, present it to people who are not very familiar with your work. Get input from a wider variety of audiences if your committee members have a diverse set of expertise.</p></li>
<li><p>Prepare a script for what you’d want to say on each slide. Time your talk about being within the given time (30 minutes in most of the departments in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saarland_University">UdS</a>).</p></li>
<li><p>Confirm with all committee members a day before the defence if they are attending regardless of the nature of the defence (in-person, online, or hybrid). There may be last-minute changes in their plans, and you might not get the information on time.</p></li>
<li><p>Test everything a couple of days ahead of the day of defence. Make sure that all the instruments and IT equipment are functional. And on the day of defence, carry a spare laptop, just in case your laptop decides to give up on you.</p>
<ol type="i">
<li>It is better to do a dry run in the venue if possible. Find and remove or manage distracting objects. The microphone was unexpectedly distracting in my case.</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>The committee members are not there to attack you, as the word “defense” implies. They will test you, I think. But have an attitude of an academic/intellectual discussant.</p></li>
<li><p>Try not to drain yourself with too much worry, anxiety, and nervousness. You know better than anyone else in the room about the content of the dissertation, the presentation, and the field of research<sup>2</sup>: go with this confidence with point 5 in mind.</p>
<ol type="i">
<li><p>Eliminate unnecessary sources of worries. Food and drinks are not primary concerns. They are manageable. Don’t put too much thought into them. Just get the damn wine and some cookies or cake or whatever. People aren’t there for food and drink. If you are like me, you’d have this conflict: “Down with the culture of PhD students serving food” vs “Attendees are my guests”. So, keep a balance. I repeat, direct your worries and concerns to their appropriate place.</p></li>
<li><p>Finding a venue can be daunting. Try to get a place as soon as you have a date fixed. Writing emails to different department secretariats and room managers, waiting for their replies only to know that the rooms are booked, checking online room portals to find out that the rooms aren’t available on the date of your defence, the contact person of the room that is available is out of office… This is another source of avoidable worry and stress which can be managed.</p></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Sleep, eat, and hydrate. Sleep well before the day of defence. If I were to do it again, I’d still organize the program in the morning, maybe at 9 and not 8. It saves hours and hours of anticipatory anxiety. You know your body; eat accordingly. Most importantly, don’t forget to take a bottle and a glass of water with you in the podium or stage. The 90-plus minutes of speaking dries your mouth, and you need hydration anyway. Sipping water also gives some time to organize your thoughts before responding to questions.</p></li>
<li><p>You don’t have answers to all questions, especially the ones you did not anticipate and those that come from the point of view you had never considered before. It is okay not to know the exact answer to some questions. But, speculate. Formulate your speculation based on your data and results and the literature.</p></li>
<li><p>Get to know your committee members: their papers, other committees they have been in, the questions they tend to ask, and how <em>kind</em> they are<sup>3</sup>. Knowing your committee’s expertise, where they come from, and where they take you with their questions will help you anticipate some questions and prepare accordingly. For example, someone might focus more on experimental methods, while another member might focus on theoritical part of your research.</p></li>
<li><p>Read. Make sure your dissertation is fresh in your mind while you are presenting and answering questions. It is tempting to think that you know what you’ve written. Of course you <em>know</em>. But do you know what statements could stand out as peculiar to the committee, to a reviewer who reads your dissertation? Be safe, do not falter while answering questions pertaining to such peculiarities. So, read. Side benefit: you’ll freshen up the citations in your memory.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>There is always a next thing to do. A new thing to worry about. I passed PhD, and now I’m worrying about getting a postdoc position of my fit/choice. In hindsight, as time passes, what you accomplished doesn’t seem too big of a deal, past worries seem too exaggerated. But in the moment, the best thing to do is to manage the concerns and try to perform well. If you are preparing for a PhD defence, I wish you all the best!</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: I gave a brief presentation on this topic at Saarland University on 09.02.2023. Find the slides <a href="https://mfr.osf.io/render?url=https%3A%2F%2Fosf.io%2Fdownload%2Fpjdgr%2F%3Fview_only%3D6e0ed43d6b844161aa95315af23c3d94%26direct%3D%26mode%3Drender">here</a>.</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>It is important to ask for help and support. I leaned on some people for help. My friends and colleagues dedicated their time and effort to make sure that I could make the computer work for online participants, and there were food and drinks, and I was not much nervous.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I know this is a cliché. It is tough, especially when the defence date is very close. But my experience is that the more you practise, the more it helps build confidence: You’ll realise more clearly what the breadth and depth of your knowledge are, and the weak points you could work on.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Don’t rely on kindness!↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>PhD</category>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>2023</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-01-21_phd-afterthought/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2023-01-21_phd-afterthought/buddha-hat.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Speaking fast and slow</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/speech-rate_Lerner2014.png" alt="Figure of waveform of audio samples of different speed." style="width:100%" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">
Fig.1 - Schematic representation of waveforms of different speech rates of clean speech. Taken from Lerner et al., 2014
</figcaption>
</figure>
<!-- ![](speech-rate_Lerner2014.png){fig-align="center"} -->
<p>In previous studies, we found that at a moderate level of speech degradation, listeners use context information that they attend to and use it to form predictions about the word that comes next in a sentence.</p>
<p>Let’s take a very simplified example. Imagine you are speaking to someone over a cellphone, and the signal is poor, which distorts the speech that you hear. It is strenuous. Nonetheless, most of the time, you carry on the conversation successfully. How? You use the information from the context and “predict” what the other person will say next when their speech is moderately distorted, and you are attending to the context.</p>
<p>What would happen if the other person speaks faster or slower than they’d generally speak?</p>
<p>To answer similar questions, we conducted two experiments with two groups of native German speakers. In Experiment 1, they listened to the sentences presented at a normal and fast speech rate (<em>0.65x</em>), while in Experiment 2, they listened to the sentences presented at a normal and slow speech rate (<em>1.35x</em>). Apart from the speed, sentences were identical in both experiments: 120 high and 120 low predictability sentences were presented. For example, <em>Sie findet die Bälle</em> (EN: She finds the balls) is a low predictability sentence, and <em>Sie jonliert die Bälle</em> (EN: She juggles the balls) is a high predictability sentence. We expected that when the speech rate increases (i.e., fast speech), processing demand for degraded speech increases. Furthermore, listeners have lesser time than normal speech to process the context information. Hence, forming predictions is difficult and less efficient. On the other hand, we expected that when the speech rate decreases (i.e., slow speech), the processing demand for degraded speech reduces. Listeners have more time than normal speech to process the unfolding speech, including the context. Hence, the intelligibility of degraded speech increases and the contextual facilitation is amplified compared to the normal speech rate.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/e1fast.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<table class="table">
<caption>Estimated effects of the model accounting for the correct word recognition in Experiment 1</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 24%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Fixed effects</th>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Std. Error</th>
<th>z value</th>
<th>p value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>1.34</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>5.58</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Speech rate (Fast)</td>
<td>-.98</td>
<td>.24</td>
<td>-4.16</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Target word predictability (High)</td>
<td>2.42</td>
<td>.28</td>
<td>8.55</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Speech rate x target word predictability</td>
<td>1.06</td>
<td>.42</td>
<td>2.50</td>
<td>.012</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>As we had expected, the results of Experiment 1 showed a significant interaction between speech rate and predictability. Contextual facilitation decreased as the speech rate increased. Importantly, the decrease was driven by the reduced word recognition in the low predictability sentences; lexico-semantic cues in the high predictability sentences are more robust than in low predictability sentences. When the processing time is short, it reduces the activation of likely sentence endings, especially when the context is less constraining.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/e2slow.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<table class="table">
<caption>Estimated effects of the model accounting for the correct word recognition in Experiment 2</caption>
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 24%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
<col style="width: 18%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Fixed effects</th>
<th>Estimate</th>
<th>Std. Error</th>
<th>z value</th>
<th>p value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Intercept</td>
<td>1.41</td>
<td>.23</td>
<td>6.20</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Speech rate (Slow)</td>
<td>-.08</td>
<td>.14</td>
<td>-.57</td>
<td>.568</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Target word predictability (High)</td>
<td>2.58</td>
<td>.30</td>
<td>8.65</td>
<td>&lt;.001</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Speech rate x target word predictability</td>
<td>.44</td>
<td>.27</td>
<td>1.65</td>
<td>.099</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The results of Experiment 2, however, were not as we had expected. The word recognition accuracy did not increase with a decrease in speech rate (i.e., when the speech became slower). Slow speech provides more time to process the (context) information but does not increase word recognition disproportionately in high or low predictability sentences. It indicates that although slow speech reduces the effortful listening of degraded speech, it does not benefit comprehension and contextual facilitation any more than normal speech.</p>
<p>In short, the findings of our experiments show that slowing down a moderately degraded speech does not amplify the facilitatory effect provided the context information. However, an increase in speech rate has a detrimental impact on identifying words that are less predictable from the context. <!--If your conversation partner speaks slow, it likely doesn’t help you understand them any better over the cellphone when the signal is weak, and the speech is moderately degraded.
But, if they are speaking faster than usual, it’s better that you ask them not to do so.
Of course, the same applies to you too ;)--></p>
<!-- As in any scientific study, this study also has its limitations (e.g., only two distinct speech rates as fast and slow speech), which I'll discuss in the future posts. -->
<!--The major one is that we have only used two distinct speech rates as the fast and slow speech to compare with the normal speech rate.
At other slower speech rates, the effect of predictability could be amplified.
We have only considered word recognition accuracy as the dependent variable. 
Other measures like RT or neural oscillations could provide a better understanding of how a change in speech rate affects language comprehension (e.g., timecourse, neural correlates). -->
<hr>
<p>Lerner, Y., Honey, C. J., Katkov, M., &amp; Hasson, U. (2014). Temporal scaling of neural responses to compressed and dilated natural speech. <em>Journal of Neurophysiology, 111</em>(12), 2433–2444. https://doi.org/10.1152/jn.00497.2013</p>
<p>Strauß, A., Kotz, S. A., &amp; Obleser, J. (2013). Narrowed expectancies under degraded speech: Revisiting the N400. <em>Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience, 25</em>(8), 1383–1395. https://doi.org/10.1162/jocn_a_00389</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>predictive processing</category>
  <category>speech perception</category>
  <category>auditory processing</category>
  <category>speech rate</category>
  <category>2022</category>
  <category>AMLaP</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Aug 2022 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-08-08_speech-rate/speech-rate_Lerner2014.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="90" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Attention is mostly what you need</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-07-25_attention-prediction/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<p>A couple of days ago, our <a href="https://mfr.osf.io/render?url=https%3A%2F%2Fosf.io%2Fdownload%2Ftdvhs%2F%3Fdirect%3D%26mode%3Drender">paper</a> on the role of attention in the facilitatory effect of predictability in the comprehension of degraded speech was published in <em><a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/langcog.2022.16">Language and Cognition</a></em>.</p>
<p>In an earlier <a href="https://mfr.osf.io/render?url=https%3A%2F%2Fosf.io%2Fdownload%2Fnuv36%2F%3Fdirect%3D%26mode%3Drender">paper</a> published in the section Auditory Cognitive Neuroscience of Frontiers in Psychology, we had shown that listeners utilize context in a sentence that facilitates their comprehension of a degraded speech. Say, in a high predictability sentence like, “<em>She dribbles the ball</em>”, identification of “<em>ball</em>” is facilitated by its preceding context compared to a low predictability sentence like, “<em>She buys a ball</em>”. This <em>Language and Cognition</em> paper shows that such facilitation is possible <em>only</em> when listeners pay attention to the sentence context and process it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-07-25_attention-prediction/attention2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In one experiment, we asked participants to listen to a degraded speech and report only the final word of a sentence they heard. It restricted their attention to the target word at the sentence-final position (e.g., “<em>ball</em>”). In another experiment, they were asked to report the entire sentence. This task did not restrict their attention to any part of the sentence; they could attend to the sentence context that preceded the target word. The results showed that the effect of predictability—a significant difference in the accuracy of recognition of the words like “ball” between high and low predictability sentences—was observed only in the second case when the participants reported the entire sentence. While reporting only the final word, there was no such effect of predictability.</p>
<p>Our findings suggest that when they report only the sentence-final target word, listeners’ attention is restricted to a particular time point as the speech unfolds in time. They do not process the context information that precedes the target word. Hence, there was no effect of predictability. On the contrary, while reporting the entire sentence, they also attend to the sentence context. They process the context information forming predictions about upcoming linguistic units; in this case, the prediction is about the sentence-final target word. Accuracy is lower for words that are less predictable from the context than those that are more predictable from the context.</p>
<p>All in all, our findings show that prediction in language processing is not an <em>automatic</em> process. Especially in an adverse listening condition, listeners have to attend to the context information to get any benefit from the context. In other words, attention is a prerequisite to processing context information and generating linguistic predictions.</p>
<p>Attention is <del>all</del> you need. Not all, but something you need to start with.</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>predictive processing</category>
  <category>speech perception</category>
  <category>auditory processing</category>
  <category>attention</category>
  <category>2022</category>
  <category>AMLaP</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-07-25_attention-prediction/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jul 2022 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2022-07-25_attention-prediction/attention.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="77" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Bookmarking conferences</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-25-cogsci-programs/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- Oh, so some links brought you here. Cool.\ -->
<hr>
<p>Many of my colleagues who consider themselves ‘doing’ cognitive science don’t seem to be aware of the conferences that the other person in the group attends. Cog. Sci. is a broad field, and it is not possible to keep up with the conferences, journals, and publications across all domains. Nonetheless, it might be helpful to keep track of, and attend if possible, the conferences that cover the common areas of interest. Here I am curating a list of conferences, some of which I have attended and some I’d like to attend.</p>
<p><br> This is nowhere near an exhaustive list; it is updated regularly.<sup>1</sup> If it helps you, great! If not, at least I have a bookmark for myself <l> 😅 </l></p>
<table class="table">
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th></th>
<th>Program</th>
<th>Date</th>
<th>Abstract submission deadline</th>
<th>Format</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>1</td>
<td>Annual (CUNY) Conference on Human Sentence Processing (<a href="https://hsp2022.ucsc.edu/">35th HSP</a>)</td>
<td>March 24 - March 26</td>
<td>Dec 06, 2021</td>
<td>Online &amp; Santa Cruz, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>2</td>
<td>Annual meeting of Cognitive Neuroscience Society (<a href="https://www.cogneurosociety.org/submit_a_poster/">29th CNS</a>)</td>
<td>April 23 - April 26</td>
<td>Jan 11</td>
<td>San Francisco, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>3</td>
<td>Association for Psychological Sciences Annual Convention of Psychological Science (<a href="https://www.psychologicalscience.org/conventions/2022-aps-annual-convention/cfs">APS 2022</a>)</td>
<td>May 26 - May 29</td>
<td>Feb 07</td>
<td>Chicago, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>4</td>
<td>Meeting of the Acoustical Society of America (<a href="https://acousticalsociety.org/asa-meetings/">182nd ASA</a>)</td>
<td>May 23 - May 27</td>
<td>Jan 24</td>
<td>Denver, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>5</td>
<td>Society for the Improvement of Psychological Science (<a href="https://www.improvingpsych.org/SIPS2022/">SIPS 2022</a>)</td>
<td>June 27 - June 29</td>
<td>March 21</td>
<td>Victoria, Canada</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>6</td>
<td>Annual conference of the Cognitive Science Society (<a href="https://cognitivesciencesociety.org/submissions/">CogSci 2022</a>)</td>
<td>July 26 - July 29</td>
<td>Feb 01</td>
<td>Online &amp; Toronto, Canada</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>7</td>
<td><a href="https://interspeech2022.org/index.php/papers/">Interspeech</a></td>
<td>Sep 18 - Sep 22</td>
<td>March 21</td>
<td>Incheon, South Korea</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>8</td>
<td>Architectures and Mechanisms for Language Processing (<a href="https://amlap2022.york.ac.uk">AMLaP 2022</a>)</td>
<td>Sep 07 - Sep 09</td>
<td>May 06</td>
<td><em>NA</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>9</td>
<td>Society for the Neurobiology of Language (<a href="https://www.neurolang.org/">SNL</a>)</td>
<td>Oct 06 - Oct 08</td>
<td>May 25</td>
<td>Philadelphia, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>10</td>
<td>Psychonomic Society 2022 Annual Meeting (<a href="https://www.psychonomic.org/page/2022AnnualMeeting">Psychonomic</a>)</td>
<td>November 17 - November 20</td>
<td>June 01</td>
<td>Online &amp; Boston, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>11</td>
<td>Neuroscience 2022 - Society for Neuroscience (<a href="https://www.sfn.org/meetings/neuroscience-2022">SfN</a>)</td>
<td>Nov 12 - Nov 16</td>
<td>June 21</td>
<td>San Diego, US</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>12</td>
<td>Symposium for Cognitive Auditory Neuroscience (<a href="https://events.mcs.cmu.edu/scan2021/#:~:text=The%20Symposium%20for%20Cognitive%20Auditory,lively%20gathering%20in%20Pittsburgh%2C%20PA.">SCAN</a>)</td>
<td>throughout <em>2022</em></td>
<td><em>NA</em></td>
<td><em>NA</em></td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>13</td>
<td>22nd Conference of the European Society for Cognitive Psychology (<a href="https://escop2022.org/submit-a-symposium-or-an-abstract">ESCOP 2022</a>)</td>
<td>Aug 29 - Sep 01</td>
<td>April 01</td>
<td>Lille, France</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>14</td>
<td>Joint Conference on Language Evolution, <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/joint-conf-language-evolution/important-dates?authuser=0">2022</a></td>
<td>Sep 05 - Sep 08</td>
<td>Feb 01</td>
<td>Online &amp; Kanazawa, Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>15</td>
<td>60th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (<a href="https://www.2022.aclweb.org/">ACL 2022</a>)</td>
<td>May 22 - May 27</td>
<td>Nov 15, 2021</td>
<td>Online &amp; Dublin, Ireland</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>16</td>
<td>Federation of European Neuroscience Societies (<a href="https://forum.fens.org/">FENS Forum 2022</a>)</td>
<td>July 09 - July 13</td>
<td>Feb 22</td>
<td>Paris, France</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>17</td>
<td>Salzburg Mind Brain Annual Meeting (<a href="https://samba.ccns.sbg.ac.at/samba-2022/register-and-submit-abstracts/">SAMBA 2022</a>)</td>
<td>July 14 - July 15</td>
<td>April 29</td>
<td>Salzburg, Austria</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>18</td>
<td>International Max Planck Research School for Language Sciences (IMPRS) Conference <a href="https://www.mpi.nl/imprs-conference">2022</a></td>
<td>June 01 - June 03</td>
<td>March 22</td>
<td>Online &amp; Nijmegen, the Netherlands</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Okay, these programs lean towards psychology and auditory &amp; language sciences. They do not cover many other domains within cognitive science. <a href="mailto:pratikbhandarinp+blog@gmail.com?">Let me know</a> about other better-not-miss conferences, symposia and summer schools.<!-- https://direct.mit.edu/opmi/issue # Note this journal. --></p>
<p>Among the ones that I have attended, the following summer schools/workshops have been quite helpful:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology (<a href="https://vasishth.github.io/IntroBayesSMLP2021/">SMLP</a>)</li>
<li>Neuromatch academy (<a href="https://academy.neuromatch.io">NMA</a>)</li>
<li>…</li>
</ol>
<p>Happy learning!</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>This post was first published on May 25, 2021; last updated: April 16, 2022.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>conference</category>
  <category>2021</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-25-cogsci-programs/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-25-cogsci-programs/pratik-pickering_attlis.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why not pick your brain</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-09-06-misc-repo-of-things/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- Oh, so some links brought you here. Cool.\ -->
<hr>
<p>I am in the Fifth Summer School on Statistical Methods for Linguistics and Psychology (<a href="https://vasishth.github.io/smlp2021/">SMLP 2021</a>). While reading this <a href="https://vasishth.github.io/bayescogsci/book/">textbook</a> recommended by the summer school instructors, I realized I needed a refresher on a few mathematical notations, among many other things. Some of these are on set theory and logical conditionals.</p>
<p>I’ve linked some Wikipedia articles that helped me refresh my high school maths and gain new knowledge. Wanna see?</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glossary_of_mathematical_symbols">Glosarry of mathematical symbols</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_set">Power set</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain_of_a_function">Domain of a function</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Codomain">Codomain of a function</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Material_conditional">Material conditional/material implication</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Predicate_(mathematical_logic)">Predicate (in matematical logic)</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Limit_ordinal">Limit ordinal</a></p></li>
</ol>
<p>Perhaps, someday in the distant future, I will write about applying these ideas in my work or not. Let’s see.</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>summer school</category>
  <category>statistics</category>
  <category>mathematics</category>
  <category>2021</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-09-06-misc-repo-of-things/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Sep 2021 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-09-06-misc-repo-of-things/hasse-powerset.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="109" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Relaxed restrictions in Saarbrücken</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-22_relaxed-rules/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<hr>
<p>Starting this Saturday (May 22), restaurants, pubs, bars and cafés will return to business in Saarbrücken. Up to 10 people are allowed to gather outdoors. This number is set to 5 for any in-house gathering. <sup>1</sup></p>
<p>Anyway, the point is – to book a table for a weekend lunch or an evening drink in a pub, you need to get a rapid antigen test report. If the test result is negative, you are a free bird for 24 hours!<br>
<a href="https://saarland-schnelltest.de">Here</a> you can find more details and book an online appointment for the test.</p>
<p>
Enjoy your social life responsibly 😏…until the number of cases reaches the threshold of <em>danger</em> leading back to restrictions.
</p>
<p>See you somewhere in <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Gastst%C3%A4tte+Tante+Anna/@49.2324397,6.995924,17z/data=!3m2!4b1!5s0x4795b41dabb2173d:0x88f91938815edbc5!4m5!3m4!1s0x4795b41daaf38ef9:0x9e6b420d8f989f9!8m2!3d49.2324362!4d6.998118">Tante Anna</a> or <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Wallys+Irish+Pub/@49.2334069,6.9945207,17z/data=!3m2!4b1!5s0x4795b41d143479dd:0x6afd2abef63b450d!4m5!3m4!1s0x4795b41d15008d89:0x584448474b7c2732!8m2!3d49.2334069!4d6.9967094">Wallys Pub</a> — my favorites.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-22_relaxed-rules/01-sankt-johann-markt.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>
Or perhaps on a walk by the river 😌 (🎵<a href="https://youtu.be/Oextk-If8HQ?t=44">and make me complete</a>🎵)
</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-22_relaxed-rules/02-saar-river.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Check the websites of <a href="https://www.rki.de/DE/Content/InfAZ/N/Neuartiges_Coronavirus/nCoV_node.html;jsessionid=E1A7C79F0AE54D3C150C23C38606E95B.internet102">Robert Koch Institute</a> and <a href="https://www.saarland.de/DE/portale/corona/home/home_node.html">Saarland state government</a> for official information, rules and regulations. The information in this page are taken from the news sources – <a href="https://www.sr.de/sr/home/nachrichten/politik_wirtschaft/coronaregeln_saarlandmodell_bundesnotbremse_100.html"><code>[1]</code></a> and <a href="https://www.sr.de/sr/home/nachrichten/politik_wirtschaft/coronaregeln_saarlandmodell_bundesnotbremse_100.html"><code>[2]</code></a>.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>covid</category>
  <category>germany</category>
  <category>2021</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-22_relaxed-rules/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2021-05-22_relaxed-rules/01-sankt-johann-markt.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Glimpsing through Meditation</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2020-07-23-glimpsing-through-meditation/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- Oh, so some links brought you here. Cool.\ -->
<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2020-07-23-glimpsing-through-meditation/meditation-01.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I was first introduced to the formal practice of meditation when I was in lower secondary school. After that, there were many instances of following spiritual schools and gurus for the sake of learning <em>how to meditate</em>. It was never consistent, and I was never consistent. In the past few months, I have consistently meditated just by myself. Without a teacher, however, learning the skill of meditation is not an easy task to undertake. After weighing the pros and cons, I decided to learn from a teacher who is trained and knows better and can teach. I came across this <a href="https://www.wakingup.com/">app</a> by Sam Harris in which there are different courses and routes of meditation practice, including one for beginners. [Sam is generally known for his expression on politics, philosophy, and religion. But this is not my concern at the moment.] Today marks the 25th day of my regular practice of following a guided meditation. I would recommend it to anyone. With the practice, I have begun to realize those aspects of ‘myself’ that had gone unnoticed earlier or had been noticed in readings. I have questions about life and existence, about self and consciousness, more than ever before. Probably this also depends on what one seeks from meditation. Why do you (want to) meditate? Do you think that meditation is the remedy to all the problems in your life: stress, negative emotions, anger, and so on? Maybe this is not the right approach to meditation, I opine. I definitely do not qualify to make a seasoned claim. But gleaning what I have glimpsed recently and what I had learnt from my intermittent practice in the past is that meditation is not the means to attain those ends. Meditation, I think, is about being mindful of the existence — the existence of thoughts, emotions, feelings, and sensations in one’s conscious awareness. Realizing and observing that everything we experience in our waking hours (probably while we sleep too) is merely the appearance of those experiences in the field of conscious awareness. And we identify this experience as ‘self’, an illusory self. This realization, even if momentary in the beginning, is enlightening [I am not using the word ‘enlightening’ in the same sense used in different Buddhist and Hindu traditions.] I can’t say for sure if I am under an illusion that I have glimpsed it: there are instances during meditation when I have momentarily observed the non-existence of ‘self’; there is no ‘I’. This might as well be an illusion in the end. With time and practice, things will be clearer for me. After all, you can see how often the word ‘<strong>I</strong>’ has been used in this writing — the self is extremely dominant. And semantics does matter, doesn’t it?</p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>germany</category>
  <category>2020</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2020-07-23-glimpsing-through-meditation/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2020-07-23-glimpsing-through-meditation/meditation-02.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>‘शहरको कथा’</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-08-19-saharko-katha/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- Oh, so some links brought you here. Cool.\ -->
<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-08-19-saharko-katha/saharko-katha.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>देशमा लोकतन्त्र स्थापनापछिको परिवेशमा शहर (विशेषत: काठमाण्डौ)मा देखिएको ’परिवर्तन’लाई लेखकले उतार्न प्रयास गरेका छन् | काठमाडौँबाहिर बाट ठुल्ठूला सपना बोकेर राजधानी खाल्डो छिरेका फरकफरक पृष्ठभूमिका फरकफरक युवतीहरुको कथालाई “म” पात्रका माध्यमबाट जोडिएको छ | पृष्ठभूमि जे भएपनि सङ्घर्षका समान कथा बोकेका छन् तिनले | बीचमा धेरै उतारचढाव बोकेपनि उपन्यासको अन्त्यसम्म आइपुग्दा ती पात्रका कथा पनि अलगअलग धारमा पुगेर टुङ्गिन्छन् | सङ्घर्षका क्रममा कोही सफल हुन्छन् त कोही असफल; तर मनैदेखि कोही सन्तुष्ट नरहेको देखिन्छ | उपन्यासले द्वन्द्वकालपछि देशको फेरिएको राजनीतिक परिवेश, अराजक सामाजिक मनोवृत्ति, द्वन्द्वको घाउमा मलमपट्टी लगाउने नाममा विदेशी गैरसरकारी संस्थाहरुले गरेको डलरको खेती, शहरी युवाहरुमा खुल्दै गएको यौनिक मानसिकता लगायतका कुरा समेटेको छ | अझै सुधार गरिनुपर्ने ठाउँ भएपनि पत्रकारिताको शैलीमा लेखिएको यस उपन्यासमा किशोर नेपालले गरेको प्रयास प्रसंशनीय छ | उत्कृष्ट नै नभएपनि “शहरको कथा” पढ्न लायक भने छ |</p>
<p><em>Republished in April 2021</em></p>
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>book review</category>
  <category>nepal</category>
  <category>2012</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-08-19-saharko-katha/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2012 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-08-19-saharko-katha/saharko-katha-preview.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>पाँचौँ लोकतन्त्र दिवस</title>
  <dc:creator>Pratik Bhandari</dc:creator>
  <link>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-04-18-fifth-loktantra-diwas/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<!-- Oh, so some links brought you here. Cool.\ -->
<hr>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-04-18-fifth-loktantra-diwas/loktantra.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>२०६९ बैशाख ६, आजभन्दा ठीक पाँच वर्षअघि झापा सदरमुकाम चन्द्रगढीमा जनआन्दोलनका बेला जिल्लाका कुना-कुनाबाट आएका हजारौं जनताको भीडमाथि तत्कालीन शाही सेनाले बर्बरतापूर्ण ढङ्गले गोलीको वर्षा गरेको घटना मेरो मस्तिष्कमा अझैपनि ताजा छ| लाठी, अश्रुग्याँस, गोली केहीको पनि पर्वाह नगरी जनताको मुक्तिको लागि निरंकुशताविरुद्धको आन्दोलनमा सहभागी एउटा बालकको रूपमा आफूलाई सम्झिँदा छाती गर्वले ढक्क हुन्छ| २०६३ बैशाख ६ गतेको उक्त घटनामा शहादत प्राप्त गर्ने अमर झापाली सपुतहरु: सूरज विश्वास र राजन गिरी प्रति हार्दिक श्रद्दाञ्जली!!!</p>
<p>शहिदको सपना साकार पार्न नेपाली समाज र राजनीति सफल रहोस् भन्ने कामना पनि व्यक्त गर्दछु!!</p>
<p>… २०६९ बैशाख ६ का दिन लेखिएको यो पोस्ट आज २०७८ बैशाख १२ का दिन हेर्दा लाग्छ, त्यतिबेला धेरै निराशा थिएन। अहिले…</p>
<p><em>Republished in April 2021</em></p>
<!--

::: {.cell}
::: {.cell-output-display}
![](loktantra.jpg){width=50%}
:::
:::

-->
<div <b="" style="text-align:center;">Signup to my newsletter for updates.
</div>
<iframe src="https://drpratik.substack.com/embed" width="800" height="150" style="border:1px solid #EEE; background:white;" frameborder="0" scrolling="no">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>nepal</category>
  <category>2012</category>
  <guid>https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-04-18-fifth-loktantra-diwas/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 18:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://pratikb.com/contents/blog/posts/2012-04-18-fifth-loktantra-diwas/loktantra.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
